There are all kinds of claims about
the red wine compound reseveratrol.
In this 4-video series
I dive into the research
as to the potential benefits and side-
effects of resveratrol supplementation.
"Does Resveratrol Make You Live Longer?"
Resveratrol, known as
the red wine molecule,
became a household word in 1991
when a scientist
from Bordeaux University
appeared on the popular TV show
"60 Minutes"
and attributed
the so-called French Paradox
to the French habit
of drinking red wine.
The term "French Paradox"
itself
was coined in the newsletter
of the International
Organization of Vine and Wine
to explain a curious finding.
If you chart death
from heart attack
versus the amount
of saturated fat
and cholesterol consumed
in different countries,
there appears to be
a straight line.
The more animal-based foods
populations eat,
the higher their death rates
appear to be.
However, two countries
didn't fall in line
with that straight line.
Finland seemed to be doing
worse than expected,
and France appeared to be doing
better than expected.
Hence, the paradox.
How could France
have saturated fat
and cholesterol intake
similar to Finland,
but five times fewer
fatal heart attacks?
Everyone had their pet theories
to explain the paradox.
Was it the wining?
Was it the dining?
Yes, animal foods
are associated
with coronary heart disease
mortality,
but plant foods
appear to be protective.
So, might the fact
that the French were eating
four times as many vegetables
help account
for their lower death rates?
It turns out, however,
that there may be
no paradox at all.
According to an investigation
by the World Health
Organization,
French physicians were
just under-reporting
heart disease deaths
on the death certificates.
So, if you correct for that,
France basically comes
right back in line
with the death
versus animal fat
and death
versus cholesterol lines,
with about four times
the fatal heart attack rates
as Japan and about four times
the animal fat consumption.
By the time of the correction,
however,
resveratrol research
had already taken root,
culminating in more than 17,000
scientific publications to date.
But only about 1 to 2 percent
of the published reports
were human clinical trials,
and after many millions
of dollars spent
and many years
of disappointing results,
the scientific tide
started to turn.
Reviews began to ask whether
resveratrol was a molecule
whose time had come and gone:
"Should we now consign
resveratrol
to our intellectual
garbage cans
and move on to better things?"
Of course,
it didn't help matters
when a leading
resveratrol researcher
was found guilty of 145 counts
of fabrication
and falsification of data,
throwing the whole field
into turmoil.
But in 2013, resveratrol
was primed to make a comeback
with the apparent confirmation
that it was a STAC,
a sirtuin-activating compound,
that is, a compound
that purportedly activates
a longevity enzyme.
This has been called
into question, though.
Commentaries with titles like
"Is resveratrol an imposter?"
"Promising therapeutic,
or hopeless illusion?"
and "The resveratrol fiasco"
were published,
suggesting that the seeming
sirtuin activity
was probably the result
of experimental artifacts.
"In summary," a recent review
concluded, "the jury is out."
The proof is in the pudding,
though.
Does resveratrol enhance
longevity or not?
Yeast is the big success story,
with resveratrol
extending the lifespan
of brewer's yeast
by up to 70 percent.
Resveratrol also helped
microscopic roundworms
live longer,
but it failed fruit flies,
mosquitoes, and water fleas.
Anything bigger than
a unicellular fungus
or a microscopic worm?
Yes, resveratrol can extend
the lives of honeybees
and, most excitingly,
two vertebrates,
short-lived fish:
Gunther's
and turquoise killifish.
Unfortunately, most studies
on mammals (mostly mice)
failed to show
a lifespan benefit.
Resveratrol is said
to extend the life
of so-called model organisms
by mimicking
calorie restriction,
but flies and mice show
robust life-extension responses
to dietary restriction,
yet don't seem responsive
to resveratrol.
That may just be true
of healthy animals, though.
Give resveratrol to mice
in extremis,
whether bombarded by radiation,
poisoned with endotoxins,
or having their intestines
punctured
to cause sepsis-induced
kidney failure,
and they do survive longer
with resveratrol
than they otherwise would
under those circumstances.
Resveratrol
can also help mediate
the life-shortening effects
of high-fat diets in mice.
The lifespans
of healthy mice and rats
fed normal diets are not
affected by resveratrol,
but the compound
partially prevented
the premature deaths of mice
fed high-fat diets.
The authors of a meta-analysis
of the effect of resveratrol
on longevity across species
concluded
that, based on the fact
that most mouse studies
failed to show a benefit,
it's "inappropriate
for resveratrol to be marketed
as a life-extending
health supplement."
True, no study has demonstrated
resveratrol lifespan extension
in healthy rodents,
only in "metabolically
compromised mammals,"
but isn't that
a pretty accurate description
of most of the U.S. population
these days?
Studies on monkeys fed diets
high in butterfat and sugar
found that resveratrol
decreased
artery and abdominal fat
inflammation.
Combined with the shift
towards normalizing
the lifespans of mice
on high-fat diets,
pharmacology journal
commentaries
were published with titles
like "Resveratrol—pills
to replace a healthy diet?"
speculating whether
"resveratrol is the compound
that will allow us to be
more and more inactive
while eating too much
in general
and too much fat and sugar
in particular."
Yes, a nutrition journal
editorial entitled
"Dodging physical activity
and a healthy diet" conceded,
exercise and dietary
modification
are the "most potent, cheapest,
and easiest ways
to prevent lifestyle-related
chronic diseases,"
but might resveratrol
on its own
"take the edge
off the consequences
of your lifestyle?"
No wonder annual sales
of resveratrol supplements
reached $30 million
in the U.S. alone.
Approaching the peak
in interest
around the time Oprah Winfrey
mentioned it in 2009,
it was estimated
that two-thirds of people
in the United States taking
multiple daily
dietary supplement regimens
included resveratrol.
But what does
the human data show?
I'll cover that, next.